<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A direction to be observed by N.N. if hee meane to proceede in answering the booke intituled Mercy and truth, or charity maintained by Catholiks &amp;c.</title>
            <author>Knott, Edward, 1582-1656.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1636</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 47 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A15510</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25777</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S101801</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837604</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99837604</idno>
            <idno type="VID">1936</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A15510)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1936)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1401:07)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A direction to be observed by N.N. if hee meane to proceede in answering the booke intituled Mercy and truth, or charity maintained by Catholiks &amp;c.</title>
                  <author>Knott, Edward, 1582-1656.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 5-42 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[Printed at the English secret press] Permissu superiorum,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London?] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1636.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Mercy and truth" is by Edward Knott, the name Matthew Wilson adopted in 1602 and kept for the rest of his life.</note>
                  <note>Printer from STC.</note>
                  <note>An attempt to discredit in advance the arguments of N.N.'s [i.e. William Chillingworth's] "The religion of protestants a safe way to salvatoin"--STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:1936:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1936:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DIRECTION TO BE OBSERVED <hi>By N. N.</hi> If hee meane to
proceede in Anſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wering the Booke intituled <hi>Mercy</hi> and <hi>Truth,</hi>
or <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity Maintained</hi> by Catholiks &amp;c.</p>
            <q>
               <p>For I ſay by the grace that is giuen me, to all that are among
you, not to be more wiſe then behoueth to be wiſe, but to be wiſe vnto
ſobrietie.</p> 
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Ad Roman. 12. v. 3.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>When we treate of religion, that is, of the worſhip and
knowledge of God, they are leaſt to be follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, who promiſing moſt
liberally proofes by <hi>reaſon,</hi> forbid vs to <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue. S. Aug. De
vtil. Cred. cap.</hi> 12.</p> 
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Permiſſu Superiorum, 1636.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:1936:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:1936:2"/>
            <head>A DIRECTION TO BE OBSERVED</head>
            <byline>By N. N.</byline>
            <head type="sub">If he meane to proceede in Anſwering the Booke
intituled <hi>Mercy</hi> and <hi>Truth,</hi> or, <hi>Charity Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained</hi>
by Catholiks &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N regard that hee, who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends to be anſwering the Booke
intituled <hi>Mercy and Truth,</hi> or, <hi>Charity Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained</hi> by
Catholicks &amp;c.: Is ſtrongly reported to be a <hi>Socinian:</hi> before I
giue him his <hi>charge,</hi> it will be requiſite, to open in brief, what
kinde of people they be, who haue appeared of late vnder the name of
<hi>Socinians.</hi> For by this meanes, it will be ſeene, whether his true
intention be, to defend <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtantiſme,</hi> or couertly to vent
<hi>Socini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aniſme.</hi> 
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:1936:3"/>It will alſo appeare, whether all
his paines be taken to any purpoſe. For <hi>Charity Maintained</hi> hauing
been written againſt <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> not inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medling with the
Doctrine of <hi>Socini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> he will neuer by thought to ſpeake one word
to the purpoſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt that Booke, if he anſwer out of Principles, which
<hi>Proteſtants</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues will profeſſe to deteſt, no
leſſe then <hi>Catholicks</hi> doe.</p>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> Of Socinianiſme.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>SOcinians</hi> take their name from one <hi>Fanſtus
Socinus,</hi> an Italian Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtata, that is, vpon the matter, an Atheiſt.
For they are ſtrangers to that wiſe and gallant Nation, who ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, they
can by of any Religion, if they will not be Catholicks. The maine and capitall
doctrine of perfect <hi>Socinians,</hi> is, rather Negatiue, and deſtructiue
of all Faith and Religion, then poſitiue or Affirnſatiue of any 
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:1936:3"/>one. The Summe of all is this. No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ought, or can be
certainly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieued, further then it may be proued by euidence of naturall
reaſon, into which they reſolue all Chriſtian<note n="(a)" place="margin">Irenaeus Philalethes lib. cui titu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus: Diſqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitio breuis
&amp;c. S. Aug. <hi>Do</hi> vtil. Cred. cap. 1. Noſti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> enim Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, non
aliam ob cauſam nos in tales ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines (Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nichaeos) incidiſſe, niſi
quod ſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cebant terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bili autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritate ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rata, mira ac ſimplici
ratione cos qui ſe audire vellent in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troducturos ad Deum, &amp; errore omni
liberaturos.</note> Faith. Out of this vniuerſall ground, they doe, and
muſt (if they will ſpeake as they thinke, and thinke according to their
owne principles) reiect all <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible, ſupernaturall, infuſed
Faith,</hi> which they reduce to meere <hi>humane knowledge,</hi> or
<hi>opinion.</hi> And this the <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerer,</hi> as I am <hi>told,</hi>
profeſſes, and endeauours to proue. They muſt then affirme, that
<hi>Faith</hi> is not <hi>donum Dei,</hi> an eſpeciall gift of God; but only
the common light of Reaſon, or habits acquired by a mans owne abilitie and
induſtrie. Diuine <hi>Faith</hi> being exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, the other two Theologicall
in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed vertues, <hi>Hope,</hi> and <hi>Charitie,</hi> cannot
ſubſiſte. All infuſed Reuelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and Prophecies; all Illuminati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
and Inſpirations of the Holy Ghoſt; all preuenient, concomitant,
ſubſequent, and, in a word, all kind of whatſoeuer <hi>ſupernaturall
Grace,</hi> is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rided by this graceleſſe <hi>Sect.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:1936:4"/>
               <p>And as they denie all ſupernaturall Faith, ſo doe they laugh
at the beliefe of all obiects, that are beyond the ſphere of naturall
diſcourſe. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they vtterly denie<note n="(b)" place="margin">Ioan.
Volkelius de vera Religione lib. <hi>5.</hi> c. <hi>9.10.11.12.13.</hi>
                  </note>
the moſt Bleſſed Trinity, the Incarnation of the Sonne of God, the
Godhead of our deare Sauiour Chriſt, his ſatisfaction for the ſinnes of
men, and his<note n="(c)" place="margin">Idem. ibid. c. <hi>20.22.</hi>
                  </note>
merit (and to proue this, they bring the ſame arguments, which Proteſtants
were wont to vrge againſt the merits of iuſt men, and works of
ſupereroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) the Diuinitie of the<note n="(d)" place="margin">Id. v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bi
ſupra. cap. <hi>14.</hi>
                  </note> Holy Ghoſt, and Originall<note n="(e)" place="margin">Id. i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid. cap. <hi>15.</hi>
                  </note> ſinne. Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall
ſupernaturall Felicitie in Heauen for the Iuſt, and endleſſe
puniſhment in Hell for the wicked, they all muſt, according to their
Principles, &amp; ſome of them doe roundly denie. And they cannot place their
laſt Happines in any thing, except ſome ſuch poore imaginarie good, as
old Pagan Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers dreamed of, but could neuer attaine, nor ſo much as
agree among themſelues, wherin it conſiſted.</p>
               <p>They denie the Reſurrection of our Bodies, and teach, that our
Soule is to <pb n="9" facs="tcp:1936:4"/>be ioyned with a Celeſtiall or ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall
ſubſtance, of a nature eſſentially different from theſe our earthlie
bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies; and that our Bleſſed Sauiour in Heauen, hath ſuch a
Celeſtiall<note n="(f)" place="margin">Vol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kel. l. <hi>3.</hi> c.
<hi>35.</hi>
                  </note> Bodie.</p>
               <p>That the world was created in <hi>time,</hi> by the free decree
of God, &amp; not from <hi>Eternitie,</hi> by a necſſarie emanation from
him, they belieue no more, then can be proued by euidence of naturall
demonſtration. And I know ſome of them hold, directly againſt holie
Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that it was from all eternitie, by ſuch a neceſſarie
reſultancie, as that.</p>
               <p>They make ſmall reckoning of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments,</hi> as being,
according to them, neither <hi>ſignes,</hi> nor <hi>ſeales,</hi> nor
<hi>cauſes</hi> of of <hi>grace;</hi> which <hi>grace,</hi> they hold to be a
meere fiction. Yea they teach, that it is an abuſe of the word
<hi>Sacrament,</hi> to apply it to<note n="(g)" place="margin">Vol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kel. l.
<hi>4.</hi> cap. <hi>22.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>holy rites.</hi> And as for the
<hi>Euchariſt</hi> in particular, one of their ring leaders teacheth, that it
is no<note n="(h)" place="margin">Ibid.</note> Sacrament; that for the matter
there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, if one cannot drinke wine, hee may vſe<note n="(i)" place="margin">Ibid.</note> water, without changing the ſubſtance of the
Lord's Supper (as he <pb n="10" facs="tcp:1936:5"/>ſpeakes) and that it may be
admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred by Lay<note n="(k)" place="margin">Ibid.</note> Perſons; and
recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued euen by ſuch, as are not<note n="(l)" place="margin">Lib. <hi>6.</hi>
cap. <hi>14.</hi>
                  </note> Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed.</p>
               <p>The ſame prime <hi>Socinian</hi> denies Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme to be a
Sacrament, and teacheth, that all are not obliged to receaue it, but that
ſome may be enrolled amongſt the number of Chriſtians, without it; that
the Church may either leaue it off, or at leaſt can compell none to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue
it; and, in a word, that it is a a thing but adiaphorous, or indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent; with
other wicked<note n="(m)" place="margin">Vide Volkel. lib. cap. <hi>6.</hi> c.
<hi>14.</hi> per. totum.</note> abſurdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, which I let paſſe.</p>
               <p>Concerning holie Scripture; to ſuch perſons, as they hold
not fit to be intirely truſted by them, they will acknowledge them all;
before other more confident friends, they reiect diuers parts of holy
Scripture, recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued euen in the Proteſtant Church of <hi>England;</hi> and
with men, who are fully acquainted with their Principles, they muſt hold, not
any one Book, Chapter, or line of the whole Old and New Teſtament, to be the
word of God, or written by the infallible aſsiſtance in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration, 
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:1936:5"/>and direction of his holy Spirit. For naturall reaſon,
which with them is the ſole <hi>Rule</hi> of <hi>Faith,</hi> &amp;
<hi>Iudge</hi> of all <hi>Controuerſies,</hi> cannot poſsibly demonſtrate
theſe things. They may belieue by a kind of Humane Faith, that the Books of
holy Scripture were written by ſuch particular men (as they belieue the
Workes of <hi>Plato, Tullie, Linie,</hi> to be theirs) but that thoſe men
were endued <hi>with</hi> an <hi>vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall infallibilitie,</hi> euen in
writing Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, they neither doe, nor can affirme, but rather reach
the<note n="(n)" place="margin">Volk. l. <hi>5.</hi> c. <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note>
contrarie.</p>
               <p>Neither yet doth their impietie ſtay here, but one of them
dares<note n="(o)" place="margin">Io. Crellius lib. de Deo, &amp; Attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butis
eius c. <hi>24.</hi>
                  </note> affirme, that God could not know from Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie
<hi>futura contingentia,</hi> ſuch things, as doe proceede from Free-Will,
and election; which is in effect, to take away all infallible predictions
pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecies of voluntarie free actions. And out of this groſſe errour,
ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther more open <hi>Socinian,</hi> will proceed to the deniall of God
himſelfe. For how can God be, and be God, ans yet be ignorant of any thing,
that is poſsible, paſt, preſent, or to come?</p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:1936:6"/>
               <p>If you aske theſe men, what they meane by the true Church;
they muſt anſwer, that there is no other true Church, but all Mankinde, as
it agrees in the light of naturall reaſon; and that there is no other
authoritie, to which a man is obliged to ſubmit.</p>
               <p>If againe you inquire, in what <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie</hi> doth indeed
conſiſte; they replie, that it conſiſtes only in oppoſing the
dictamen, or iudgement of a man's owne reaſon. They might as well ſay in
plaine termes: There is no ſuch thing, as Chriſtians are wont to call
<hi>Hereſie.</hi> For it is impoſsible, that a man iudge contrarie to that,
which he iudgeth. <hi>Intellectus non eſt hypocrita.</hi> Our vnderſtanding
cannot play the hypocrite with it ſelf. A man's hands, lookes, words, or
writing may belie his thoughts, and make him deſerue the name of
diſſembler, falſifier, hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrite. But it implies a manifeſt
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction, that our internall thoughts ſhould tell vs, at the ſame
time, that a thing is both ſo, and not ſo; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, according to
their large defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, there can be no <hi>Hereſie</hi> at all. 
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:1936:6"/>And their aſſertions tending to <hi>pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice,</hi> are
agreable to this their <hi>ſpecula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> For they teach, that no man
ought now to be puniſhed, either ſpiritually by<note n="(p)" place="margin">Iren. Philalethes lib. cui titu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus: Diſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatio de Pace
Fccleſia.</note> Excommunication, or<note n="(q)" place="margin">Vol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kel. lib.
<hi>6.</hi> cap. <hi>15.</hi>
                  </note> tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porally, with the loſſe of goods,
im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment, or death, as long as he followes the dictamen of his owne
Conſcience; though otherwiſe he denie Articles belieued by all good
Chriſtians; as for example, concerning the moſt Bleſſed. Trinity, the
Diuinity, of Chriſt our Lord, Originall ſinne &amp;c.</p>
               <p>But why doe I ſpecifie particulars, which would be infinite?
For what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer our Sauiour Chriſt, his holy Apoſtles, the Catholicke
Church, Councels, Fathers, Doctours, Diuines, Chriſtians, propoſe to be
belieued a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue humane reaſon, or with a <hi>ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall infallible</hi>
aſſent, is, to theſe men, no other then a fiction, an impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture, an
impoſsibilitie. <hi>Diuinity,</hi> with them, can be nothing but
<hi>Philoſophie. Reaſon</hi> alone is <hi>Faith; Sanctitie</hi>
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtes only in <hi>Moralitie. Plato, or Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtotle,</hi> or any
other, muſt be as ſoone belieued, as the teſtimonie of our deare 
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:1936:7"/>Sauiour; vnles he proue what he ſaith, by better reaſon,
the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> other do,<note n="(r)" place="margin">Si autem Chriſto eti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am creden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum
negant, nili indubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tata ratio reddita ſue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ani non ſunt. Nam
id ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſus nos Pagani qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam dicunt, ſtultè qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem, ſed non
ſibi aduerſi, nec repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nantes. Hos vero quis ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratad Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtum ſe
per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinere proſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teri, qui niſi apertiſſimam rationem ſtultis de Deo
protu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerint, nihil credendum eſſe conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dunt? S. Aug. De vtil. Cred. cap.
14</note> What Chriſtian can heare theſe infidelities, without
deteſtation? What Church can tolerate them, and yet pretend zeale in
Religion? Neuertheles, this vngodlie <hi>ſect</hi> ſpreades it ſelfe,
being cunningly obtruded by ſome (and by the <hi>Anſwerer</hi> in
particular) &amp; greedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſwallowed by many, and duly pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed by none;
although I ought not to diſſemble, but doe gladly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, and
deſeruedly publiſh in this occaſion, for a patterne to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in this
Realme, the care of the chiefeſt Prelare in <hi>England,</hi> in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibiting
the ſale of Bookes tending to <hi>Socinianiſme.</hi> Let men in the meane
time ſpeake their pleaſure, againſt the vigilancie of Prolats in
Catholicke Countries; againſt the ſeueritie of Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall Canons;
againſt forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to reade pernicious bookes; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Index
Expurgatorius,</hi> and againſt the holie Office of <hi>Inquiſition</hi> in
Italie, and ſome other places. Sure I am, through want of ſuch hole ſome
meanes <hi>Hereſies, Infidelities,</hi> and <hi>Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſmes,</hi> 
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:1936:7"/>are hatched, &amp; receaue growth; and innumerable ſoules
eternally pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh. And becauſe the Reader may well remaine in wonder, how
ſo very ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd errours, can poſsibly finde enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainement among
Chriſtians: it will not by impertinent, though beſides my firſt
intention, to ſet downe ſome reaſons thereof, as they now preſent
themſelues to my minde. And they may ſerue for the argument of the
enſuing Chapter.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> Some reaſons, why ſo many embrace
Socinianiſme.</head>
               <p>TO omit, that this Hereſie giue full ſcope to euerie man's
<hi>vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding,</hi> to belieue, as his fancie ſhall dictate, and for
his will, to ſinne with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out feare of eternall puniſhment (yea and not to
belieue, that there is a God, if ſome licentious impe can obiect againſt
the Diuine Exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtence, Prouidence, Iuſtiee, Mercie, Wiſdome, or other
Artributes an <pb n="16" facs="tcp:1936:8"/>argument, which he cannot ſolue, and
maiſter the wit of whatſoeuer Atheiſt) I will, for the preſent, touch
only foure reaſons, drawne: <hi>firſt,</hi> from the doctrine of
Proteſtants; <hi>ſecondly,</hi> from the practiſe of the Church of
England, ioyned with the diſpoſition of Socini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans; <hi>thirdly,</hi> from
the perſonall quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of Proteſtant Diuines; <hi>fourthly,</hi> from
ſome circumſtances of perſons, time, and place.</p>
               <p>Firſt then, I ſay, that the verie Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Proteſtants
if it be followed cloſely, and with coherence to itſelf, muſt of
neceſsitie induce <hi>Socinianiſme.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">S. Aug. De vtil.
Cred. c. 16. Sola eſt authoritas quae commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uet ſtultos vt ad ſapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entiam
fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinent. Quandiu in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligere ſyncera non poſſamus, authoritate
quidem de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipi miſerum eſt: ſed certè miſerius non moueri. Si
enim Dei prouid<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>entis non praelid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> rebus huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis, nibil eſt de religione ſatagendum. Sin vero
&amp; ſpecies re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, quam profecto eſt aliquo veriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimae
pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chritudinis fonte manatire creden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum eſt; &amp; interiori neſcio quae
conſcientiae Deum quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendum, Deoque ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiendum, meliores quoſque
animos qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi publicè priuatimque hoteatur: non eſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperandum
ab codem ipſo Deo au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritatem aliquam conſtitutam. qua velut gradu certo
innitentes, attollamur in Deum.</note> This I ſay confidently, and euidently
proue, by inſtancing in one errour, which may well be tearmed the Capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall,
and mother Hereſie, from which, all other muſt follow at eaſe; I meane,
their hereſie in affirming, that the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petually viſible Church of
Chriſt, deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended by a neuer interrupted ſuceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion from our
Sauiour, to this day, is not infallible in all that it propoſeth to be
belieued, as reuealed truths.</p>
               <p>For if the <hi>infallibilitie</hi> of ſuch a pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blicke
<hi>Authoritie</hi> be once impeached; <pb n="17" facs="tcp:1936:8"/>what remaines, but
that euerie man is giuen ouer to his owne <hi>wit,</hi> and
<hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe?</hi> And talke not here, of holy Scripture. For if the true
Church may erte, in defining, what Scriptures be Canonicall; or in deliuering
the ſenſe and meaning thereof; we are ſtill de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolued, either vpon the
<hi>prinate ſpirit</hi> (a foolerie now exploded out of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, which
finally leauing euery man to his owne conceits, ends in
<hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinianiſme</hi>) orels vpon naturall wit, and iudgement, for examining
and determining, what Scriptures con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine true or falſe doctrine, and in
that reſpect, ought to bee receaued, or reiected. And indeed, take away the
authority of Gods Church, no man can bee aſſured, that any one Booke, or
parcell of Scripture, was written by diuine inſpiration; or that all the
contents, are infallibly true; which are the direct errours of
<hi>Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians.</hi> If it were but for this reaſon alone, no man, who
regardes the eternall ſaluation of his ſoule, would liue or dye in
<hi>Proteſtancie,</hi> from which, ſo vaſte abſurdities, as theſe of
the <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinians</hi> 
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:1936:9"/>muſt ineuitably follow. And it
ought to be an vnſpeakable comfort to all vs Catholicks, while we
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, that none can denie the infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble authoritie of our Church, but
ioyntly he muſt be left to his owne wit, and waies; and muſt abandon all
<hi>infuſed Faith,</hi> and true Religion, if he doe but vnderſtand
himſelfe aright.</p>
               <p>The ſecond reaſon, drawne from the proceeding of the Church
of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> I vnderſtand to be, that their ayme and induſtrie,
tendes only to procure an exteriour conformitie to the Lawes of the Realme. In
ſo much, that, if a Catholicke, for example, would reſort to their Church
Seruice, and Sermons; take Oath of Suprema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie; receaue their Communion, and
abiure the Catholicke Faith, though withall he proteſt to doe it only for
feare, and againſt his Conſcience; yea and that he diſlikes their
Seruice, Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, Faith, and Communion. In this caſe, they are, and muſt
be ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with the forced actions of ſuch a miſerable man, though
euen his owne <pb n="19" facs="tcp:1936:9"/>toung beare witneſſes, that all is donne
againſt his conſcience. And what is this, but to neglect the Soule, vpon
condition, to receaue ſome kinde of violent tribute from the Bodie? This then
being the ſpirit of the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> Church, on the one ſide; and
<hi>Socini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> on the other, making no ſcruple (with what honeſtie, I
leaue to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered) to ſorte themſelues, for the exteriour, with
what Religion ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer; no wonder, if by this meanes, they haue a large
ſcope, to inſtill their Doctrine; and yet walke with as much freedome, as
any Proteſtant can doe.</p>
               <p>The third reaſon, taken from the qualitie of Proteſtant
Diuines is this Socinians deſtroying all <hi>ſupernaturall</hi> beliefe, or
<hi>infallible</hi> aſſent, to any Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect, ſurpaſsing the reach of
Humane Reaſon, haue as manie, and as ſtrong obiections readie at hand,
againſt the Articles of our Faith, as the weake vnderſtanding of man doth
finde dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties, in the knowledge of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uines things. Now, the learning of
<hi>Proteſtant</hi> Diuines, conſiſting <pb n="20" facs="tcp:1936:10"/>onely in
ſome ſuperficiall talent of Preaching, languages, or elocution, &amp; not
in any deep knowledge of <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophie,</hi> eſpecially of
<hi>Metaphiſicke,</hi> and much leſſe of that moſt ſolide,
profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, ſubtile, and ſuccinct method, which wee call <hi>Schoole
Diuinitie;</hi> when they come to be preſſed by <hi>Socinians,</hi> are
vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to ſatisfie their doubts, but either are caught themſelues, as I
know it hapneth not ſeldome; or giue occaſion for the <hi>Socinians</hi> to
be more ſetled in their errours; and for others to be drawne into the ſame
infidelitie. And the Diuell aymed at no leſſe then this totall ruine of all
Faith and Religion, when he firſt moued Hereticks to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ride <hi>Schoole
Diuinitie,</hi> and to nickname the Profeſſours thereof, dunſes.</p>
               <p>The fourth reaſon, that caſts ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, eſpecially, of
the beſt wits, vpon Socinianiſme, both Diuines, and other among
Proteſtants, is, becauſe they <hi>will not</hi> be Catholicks <hi>in
theſe times;</hi> they <hi>cannot</hi> bring their vnderſtanding to be
Proteſtants; and ſo they take the large and eaſie way of helieuing, what
they liſt. And, to ſpeake the truth, <pb n="21" facs="tcp:1936:10"/>what learned
iudicious man, can, after vnpartiall examination, imbrace Proteſtantiſme?
which waxeth euen wearie of it ſelf (and this is an infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble marke of
Sects and Hereſies; for where the Holy Ghoſt Directeth, there can bee no
contrarietie, or mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tabilitie) its Profeſſours, they eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially of
greateſt worth, learning, and authoritie, declare themſelues to loue temper
and moderation, allowe of manie things, which ſome yeares agoe were vſually
condemned, as ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious and Antichriſtian; and are at this time more
vnreſolued where to faſten, then at the infancie of their Church. Thus
<hi>Truth,</hi> the Center of our vnderſtanding, maugre neuer ſo long, or
ſtrong oppoſition, worketh powerfully, though patiently, and by
inſenſible degrees, calls men backe from fierceneſſe to
doubtfulneſſe, from doubtfulneſſe to certaintie, that at length they
may ioy in a ſetled con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancie. And in this it is very appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, that the
Holy Ghoſt directs the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> which proceeding alwayes vpon
the ſame grounds, and <pb n="22" facs="tcp:1936:11"/>belieuing, that Chriſt our Lord
is ſtill preſent with his Spouſe, aſcribes as much infallibilitie to
the preſent Church, as to that of the firſt fine hundred yeares; and
reuerenceth the late Councell of <hi>Trent,</hi> no leſſe then the ancient
Councell of <hi>Nice.</hi> For the promiſes of our deare Sauiour, were not
limited for any Age; without the aſsiſtance of whoſe holy Spirit, no
times, or perſons, are exempted from errours; and with it, all are ſure not
to erre. And this is the true reaſon, why the <hi>Roman</hi> Church is
ſtill the ſame, without oppoſition to it ſelfe in any leaſt Doctrine;
whereas all other Sects, and Sectaries, are notoriouſly knowne, to contradict
both their Affociats, and themſelues, as now I was ſaying of the
Proteſtant Church in <hi>England.</hi> For doe not their Churches beginne to
looke with another face! their walles to ſpeake a new language? their
Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers to vſe a ſweeter tone? their annu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all publicke Tenets, in their
Vniuerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, to be of another ſtile, &amp; matter? their bookes to
appeare with titles and arguments, which once would <pb n="23" facs="tcp:1936:11"/>haue
cauſed a mightie ſcandall among the Brethren? their Doctrine to be altered
in manie things,<note n="(a)" place="margin">For ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, the Pope not
Antichriſt; Prayer for the Dead; Limbus Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trum; Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures; that the Church
hath autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine Controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies in Faith, and to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret the
Scripture; about Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will, and Predeſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall Grace; that al
our works are not ſins; morit of good works; inherent Iuſtice; Faith alone
doth not iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie; Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie is to be preferred before knowledge,
Traditions; Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to bee kept, &amp;c.</note> and euen
in thoſe verie points, for which their Progenitours forſooke the then
viſible Church of Chriſt? Their 39. <hi>Articles</hi> that is, the ſumme,
the Confeſsion, &amp; almoſt the Creede of their Faith, are patient;
patient? they are ambitious of ſome ſenſe, wherein they may ſeeme to be
Catholick. To alledge the neceſsitie of wife and children in theſe dayes,
is but a weake plea, for a married Miniſter, to compaſſe a Benefice.
Firie <hi>Caluiniſme,</hi> once a darling in <hi>England,</hi> is at lenght
accounted Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie; yea and little leſſe then Treaſon men, in word and
writing, vſe wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly the once fearfull names of <hi>Prieſts.</hi> and
<hi>Altars.</hi> Nay if one doe but mutter againſt the placing of the Altar
after the old faſhion, for a war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning he ſhall be well warmed by<note n="(b)" place="bottom">A little Treatiſe ſo intituled, &amp; printed An.
1636.</note> 
                  <hi>a Coale from the Altar.</hi> Engliſh Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants are now
put in<note n="(c)" place="bottom">Sunday no Sabbath. A Sermon printed An. 1636.
pag. 38.</note> minde that for expoſition of Scripture, <pb n="24" facs="tcp:1936:12"/>
                  <hi>by</hi>
                  <note n="(d)" place="margin">Lib. Can. An. <hi>1571.</hi>
Can. <hi>19.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Canon they are bound to follow</hi> the ancient
Fathers; which if they doe with ſinceritie, euery learned Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant
Diuine, who makes a conſcience to belie his owne knowledge, can tell, what
doome will paſſe againſt Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancie, euen by confeſsion of
Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants themſelues, as the <hi>Anſwerer</hi> once anouched (as
ſhall appeare here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after <hi>Chap.</hi> 5. <hi>n.</hi> 6.) and this being
only a matter of <hi>fact,</hi> and requiring no more then reading, and
vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the toungs, wherein the Fathers wrote, or the Tranſlations
of their Works, he cannot in morall honeſtie, and therefore, I hope, will
not, gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay his own words; nor can be thought to ſpeake ſincerely, if
hee ſhould for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedly now retract, what then he freely wrote. And I know, that
to ſome Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, hee ſo cleerely demonſtrated, the Fathers to bee
on our ſide, that they remained conuineed, and haue vpon occaſion
acknowledged no leſſe. But let vs goe on. The foure prime <hi>Proteſtant
Church-Chroniclers,</hi> who pretend to deduce a ſucceſsion of the true
Church (the <hi>Centuriſts,</hi> I meane) <pb n="25" facs="tcp:1936:12"/>are without
ceremonle demanded in a <hi>particular</hi> occaſion: <hi>with what face dare
they vente ſuch vntruths? and with what conſcience dare they</hi>
                  <note n="(e)" place="margin">Sunday no Sabbath. pag. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>forge &amp;c.</hi>
their bad carriage towards the ancient Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers is diſplayd; and for a
<hi>generall</hi> Cenſure, they are told, that <hi>Their credit is
eclipſed, and their teſtimonie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bated by their</hi>
                  <note n="(f)" place="margin">Ibid. pag. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>doings.</hi> And to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude all in one
maine point. The <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant</hi> Church in <hi>England,</hi> willingly
profeſſeth ſo ſmall Antiquitie, and ſo weake ſubſiſtance in it
ſelfe, that they acknowledge no other viſible being for many Ages; but in
the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> Which <hi>poſition</hi> drawne from them by
meere neceſsitie, muſt force them to yeeld, that the <hi>Roman</hi> Church
doth not erre in any point neceſſarie to Saluation, vnleſſe they haue a
minde, to bee telling the world, that in their owne Church, for many Ages, none
could be ſaued. They muſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore bee ſtill content, to heare vs tell
them againe and againe, this moſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary truth. You cannot bee
ſaued, vnleſſe you belieue, that wee in our Church are capable of
ſaluation; but <pb n="26" facs="tcp:1936:13"/>wee neither doe, nor can yeelde, that
<hi>Proteſtancie</hi> is compatible with eternall happineſſe. For, to
allow ſaluation for men, diſagreeing in Faith, Religion, and Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, is
one of the greateſt abſurdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in <hi>Turoiſme,</hi> or
<hi>Socinianiſme;</hi> and is but diſguiſed <hi>Atheiſme.</hi> Wee then
are ſafe by your owne confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; but you cannot bee ſo, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
repentance, and reunion to our Church. Beſides, if our Church en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyed all
things neceſſary to Saluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: how can <hi>Proteſtants</hi> bee
excuſed from the grieuous ſinne of formall <hi>Schiſme,</hi> who
ſeparated from that Church, for points confeſſedly not ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to
ſaluation? Yea, how are they not guilty of <hi>Schiſme,</hi> who
for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooke that Church, which, before <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> was only true Church,
if our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Chriſt had any viſible Church vpon earth? And what heighth
of dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous madnes is it, to leaue a Church, which cannot erre in points
neceſſarie to Saluation; and ioyne in <hi>beliefe</hi> and
<hi>Communion,</hi> with priuate perſons, who may deceaue, and be deceaued,
euen in <pb n="27" facs="tcp:1936:13"/>fundamentall articles of Faith? And I would gladly
know, with what vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Church exiſting before <hi>Luther,</hi> did hee
ioyne, when vpon pretence of Reformation, hee departed from all Churches
extant, when hee firſt appeared; and conſequently how can hee auoide the
iuſt imputation of <hi>Schiſme?</hi> But I will not vrge theſe points
here, refering my ſelfe, to what hath beene ſaid in <hi>Charitie
main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained</hi> and euen to what will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare in thoſe very
<hi>Motiues,</hi> which induced the <hi>Anſwerer</hi> himſelfe to leaue
<hi>Proteſtatiſme;</hi> and afterward be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing reſolued, not to remaine
Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke, as not conducing to his tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall ends, hee finally plunged
him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in <hi>Socinianiſme,</hi> ſeeing full well, that his owne
<hi>Motiues</hi> could not bee anſwered in the grounds of
<hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants.</hi> But it is time to returne, and ſhew, that I ſpoke
not without ground, in accuſing <hi>Socinians</hi> in <hi>ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall,</hi> of
ſuch vnchriſtian doctrines, as you haue heard, ſince you will ſee my
word made good in <hi>particular</hi> Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets of one of them, which at this 
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:1936:14"/>fit occaſion came to my hands; and I willingly impart
them to the Reader, as they were giuen me; yet ſo, as in charitie I conceale
the partie taxed with them, no otherwiſe then I for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare to publiſh the
name of the <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwearer.</hi> If guiltineſſe driue any one to
aske:<note n="(g)" place="margin">Math. c. <hi>26.</hi> v. <hi>25.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>Nunquid ego ſum, Rabbi?</hi> Maiſter, am I he? And that hee chance to
be anſwered<note n="(h)" place="margin">Ibid.</note>: <hi>Tu dixiſti;</hi>
Thou haſt ſaid ſo; the blame and ſhame muſt reſt on himſelfe
alone, who alone would be diſcouering himſelfe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> Diuerſe enormous Hereſies, maintained
by a certaine <hi>Socinian,</hi> contrary either to the <hi>39. Articles</hi>
of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> or to the Faith of all Chriſtians.</head>
               <p n="1">1. THat the Sonne of God is not begotten, from
euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting, of the Father: is not very, and eternall God, of one
ſubſtance with the Father; and that two whole <pb n="29" facs="tcp:1936:14"/>and
perfect natures were not ioyned in one perſon. <hi>Cont. Art.</hi> 2.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That Chriſt did not aſcend in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Heauen, in his
Bodie, with Fleſh, Bones, and all things appertaining to the perfection of
mans nature. <hi>Cont. Art.</hi> 4.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That the Holy Ghoſt doth not proceede from the
Father, and the Sonne; nor is of one ſubſtance with the Father, and the
Sonne, true and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall God. <hi>Cont. Art.</hi> 5.</p>
               <p n="4">4. That all the Books of the Old and New Teſtament, as
they are commonly receaued, are not equall in the authoritie, and infallibility
of holy Scripture. <hi>Cont. Art.</hi> 6.</p>
               <p n="5">5. That the three Creeds ought not throughly to bee
receaued, and belieued; for that they may be diſpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by moſt certaine
warrants of holy Scripture; and that among other falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoods in the Creed of
<hi>Saint Athana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius,</hi> this is one, that if a man disbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue any part
of that Creed, without doubt, hee ſhall periſh euerlaſtingly: That the
Apoſtles Creed, is no cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine and authenticall Tradition; and 
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:1936:15"/>that the Article of <hi>Holy Catholicke Church,</hi> is not
neceſſarily to be belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. <hi>Cont. Art.</hi> 8.</p>
               <p n="6">6. That Originall ſinue is not the fault and corruption
of the nature of euery man; nor deſerues Gods wrath and damnation. <hi>Cont.
Art.</hi> 9.</p>
               <p n="7">7. That any man may bee ſaued by the Law or Sects which
hee pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth; ſo that hee bee diligent to frame his life according to
that Law, and the light of Nature. <hi>Cont. Art.</hi> 18.</p>
               <p n="8">8. That the Church hath no authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in Coutrouerſies
of Faith, to oblige any mans conſcience. <hi>Cont. Art.</hi> 20.</p>
               <p n="9">9. That the Sacraments bee only Badges, or Tokens of
Chriſtian mens profeſsion. <hi>Cont. Art.</hi> 25.27. And that they bee not
neceſſary to ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. <hi>Cont. Catechiſm. Proteſtant.
Anglie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="10">10. That the Baptiſme of young Children is not to bee
retained in the Church, as moſt agreable to the inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eution of Chriſt.
<hi>Cont. Art.</hi> 27.</p>
               <p n="11">11. That the offering of Chriſt upon the Croſſe, is
not a perfect pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitiation and ſatisfaction for all the ſins of the whole
world. <hi>Cont. Art.</hi> 31.</p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:1936:15"/>
               <p n="12">12. That the true Body and Blood of Chriſt is not in
the Bleſſed Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, neither in a <hi>Reall</hi> nor <hi>Spirituall</hi>
manner; and that it is only a ſigne or token of his Body. <hi>Cont. Art.</hi>
28.</p>
               <p n="13">13. That Faith containes no infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible certaintie of the
things belieued.</p>
               <p n="14">14. That the reaſonable Soule is not immortall,
naturall, and <hi>perſe,</hi> but only <hi>per accidens;</hi> as it is added
to ſome Soules, by way of puniſhment or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, to be immortall.</p>
               <p n="15">15. That this immortality of wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked Soules is not to bee
extended, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to all eternity; and that it were vniuſt in God, to
puniſh finite offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, with infinite torments.</p>
               <p n="16">16. That no point of Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion is to be
belieued aboue Reaſon.</p>
               <p>For an <hi>Epilogue</hi> to theſe groſſe errors, I could
adde an <hi>Apologue</hi> of his owne, and lay in his diſh a couple of
<hi>Frogs.</hi> He vnderſtands my meaning.<note n="(a)" place="margin">If the
Anſwerer publiſh his Booke, and yet will, not declare his opinion
concerning cucrie one of theſe wie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked Poſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: by omitting to plead not
guiltie in that occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, euery iudicious &amp;c realous Chriſtian will
hold him to bee guiltie of them all.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Tell mee now, Chriſtian Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, what manner of man this
<hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinian</hi> is; and what it is to be a <hi>Socinian,</hi> or
<hi>Proteſtant,</hi> or any other <hi>Sectary,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying the
infallibility of Gods Church in all her definitions, concerning 
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:1936:16"/>matters of Faith? For, as I haue ſaid already,
whoſoeuer refuſeth to relie on ſuch Authoritie, muſt reſolue the
truth of his Faith, into the ſtrength of his owne <hi>wit,</hi> or, to
ſpeake more truely, of his <hi>will,</hi> which is to take away all
<hi>infallible, ſupernaturall Faith;</hi> without which (as the<note n="(b)" place="margin">Heb. c. <hi>11.</hi> v. <hi>6.</hi>
                  </note> Apoſtle auoucheth)
<hi>it is impoſſible to pleaſe God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And thus hauing ſhewed, what <hi>Socinianiſme</hi> is, and
vpon what ground it goes; I may now oportunely deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the <hi>Anſwerer</hi>
his <hi>direction,</hi> leaſt hee chance to miſtake, and in lieu of
maintaining <hi>Proteſtancie,</hi> hiddenly plant poiſon of
<hi>Socianiſme,</hi> and leaue <hi>Charitie maintained,</hi> not ſo much as
once ſpoken to, in his whole <hi>Anſwer,</hi> as I noted in the
beginning.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:1936:16"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> What the Anſwerer is to obſerue, if he
will ſpeake to any purpoſe.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>FIrſt</hi> it will be expected, that he declare his owne
opinion plainely and particularly; and not thinke to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie by a meere
deſtructiue<note n="(a)" place="margin">Sed quae rurſum ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio reuoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat, ne
apud eos (Mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaeos) peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus haererems niſi quod ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſos quoque
animaduerte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bam, plus in refellendis aliis diſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tos, &amp; copio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſos
eſſe, quam in ſuis probandis firmos &amp; certos ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere? S. Aug. De
vtilitat. Creden. cap. 1.</note> way of obiecting ſuch difficulties againſt
Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks, as, vpon examination, tend to the ouer throw of all Religion, no
leſſe then of Catholicke Doctrine.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> that his arguments de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy not ſome of
his owne Tenets.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> that he contradict not <hi>D. Potter,</hi>
whome he pretends to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fende; and who maintaines the infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libilitie of Gods
Church, in <hi>fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall</hi> Articles; the Supernaturalitie of Faith; and
diuers other points, which I know the <hi>Anſwerer</hi> laughes at.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> that he oppoſe not the 39.
<hi>Articles</hi> of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fiftly,</hi> that his grounds deſtroy not the bellefe of
the moſt Bleſſed Trinitie, <pb n="34" facs="tcp:1936:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>the Deitie of our
deare Lord and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, and of the Holy Ghoſt; Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſinne, and
diners other doctrines, which all good Chriſtians belieue; yea and all
verities, that cannot be proued by naturall Reaſon.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sxithly,</hi> that he relle not vpon ſuch Principles, as
muſt bring with them the deniall of diuers Bookes of holy Seripture, receaued
into the <hi>Canon,</hi> both by Catholicks and Proteſtants. And if he asked,
whether the Epiſtle of <hi>Saint Iames,</hi> the Apocalyps of <hi>Saint
Iohn,</hi> with ſome other parts of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, now receaued by Engliſh
Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, though heretofore controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, be Canonicall, let him not
ſtill thinke, to ſatisfie, by ſaying: <hi>Theſe are captious
queſtions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Seauenthly,</hi> that he doe not ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw the
infallibility of all Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, both of the Old and New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eightly,</hi> that his Arguments tend not to proue an
impoſsibilitie of all Diuine <hi>Supernaturall infallible Faith</hi> and
Religion, that either hath been, or is, or ſhall be, or poſsibly can
be.</p>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:1936:17"/>
               <p>But now, the reaſon, why I preuent the <hi>Anſwerer,</hi>
with theſe <hi>Directions,</hi> is this. From Truth, no man can, by good
conſequence, inferre falſhood. If then the <hi>Anſwerer</hi> produce
ſuch Arguments, as either proue nothing, or els muſt extend to proue that,
which is confeſſedly falſe, it will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine very cleare, that his
reaſons are but Sophiſmes, and artificiall falſities, though they
ſhould ſeeme not eaſie to be anſwered, eſpecially to ſuch, as are
either not learned at all, or ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perficially learned, and not verſed in
ſolid <hi>Philoſophie,</hi> or <hi>Schoole Diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie,</hi> from whence
<hi>Socinians</hi> are glad to borrow <hi>Obiections,</hi> but either
diſſemble, or vnderſtand not the <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions.</hi> Wherefore, if the
Arguments of the <hi>Anſwerer</hi> be found to beate vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſome of the
foreſayd grounds, and by that meanes appeare to proue <hi>too much,</hi>
euerie one will ſee, they proue <hi>nothing at all.</hi> And if
(not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding this <hi>Direction</hi> to the contrarie) he will be
trenching on the ſayd exceſſes, his Booke is alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy anſwered, euen
before it appeare. <pb n="36" facs="tcp:1936:18"/>But let him not interpret this my
pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uention, or Direction, to proceede from feare, that his Booke will be
vnanſwerable, and that therefore I ſeeke afore hand to diſgrace the
Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour, and foreſtall the publication: For by Gods holie aſsiſtance,
his Booke ſhall be anſwered, and the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent venome fetcht out, though
per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps he will <hi>lay wagers to the contrarie;</hi> and with his much
confidence would perſwade <hi>All Soules</hi> to belieue him. And in truth,
what greater aduantage could wee wiſh againſt Proteſtants, then that they
ſhould truſt their Cauſe, and poſsibilitie to by ſaued, with a
Champion, who often and euen not very long ſince, hath profeſſed, that he
will neuer ſubſcribe to their 39. <hi>Articles?</hi> and hath ſet downe
in writing, <hi>Motiues,</hi> which induced him to forſake
<hi>Proteſtantiſme</hi> (to which indeed he neuer returned) and which are
extant ſtill to be exhibited, if need be, vnder his owne hand. But how
ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, I preſente a copie of them, in the next, which ſhall be the
laſt, Chapter of my <hi>Direction.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:1936:18"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> The <hi>Motiues,</hi> for which the
Anſwerer for ſooke <hi>Proteſtantiſme.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1. BEcauſe perpetuall viſible pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsion, which
could neuer be wanting to the Religion of Chriſt, nor any part of it, is
apparently wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to Proteſtant Religion; ſo farre as concernes the
points in conteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Becauſe <hi>Luther</hi> and his followers,
ſeparating from the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> ſeparated alſo from all
Churches, pure or impure, true or falſe then being in the world; vpon which
ground I conclude, that either Gods promiſes did faile of performance, if
there were then no Church in the world, which held all things neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie,
and nothing repugnant to Salua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; or els that <hi>Luther</hi> and his
Secta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, ſeparating from all Churches then in the world, and ſo from the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:1936:19"/>true, if there were any true, were <hi>damnable
Schiſmaticks.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Becauſe, if any credit may be giuen to as creditable
records, as any are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant, the doctrine of Catholicks hath beene frequently
confirmed; and the oppoſite doctrine of Proteſtants, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded, with
ſupernaturall and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine Miracles.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Becauſe many points of Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant doctrine, are
the damned opinions of Hereticks, condemned by the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitiue Church.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Becauſe the Prophecies of the old Teſtament,
touching the Conuerſion of Kings &amp; Nations to the true Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of
Chriſt, haue been accompliſhed in &amp; by the Catholicke <hi>Roman</hi>
Religion, &amp; the Profeſſors of it; and not by Proteſtant Religion, and
the Profeſſors of it.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Becauſe the doctrine of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi>
is conformable, and the doctrine of Proteſtants contrary, to the doctrine of
the Fathers of the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitiue Church, euen by the confeſsion of Proteſtants
themſelues; I meane, thoſe Fathers, who liued within the compaſſe of
the firſt 600. yeares; to <pb n="39" facs="tcp:1936:19"/>whom Proteſtanrs themſelues
doe very frequently, &amp; very confidently appeale.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Becauſe the firſt pretended Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers had neither
extraordinary <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion</hi> from God, nor ordinary
<hi>Miſſion</hi> from the Church, to preach Proteſtant doctrine.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Becauſe <hi>Luther,</hi> to preach againſt the
Maſſe (which containes the moſt materiall points now in Controuerſie)
was perſwaded by reaſons ſuggeſted to him by the Diuell himſelfe,
diſputing with him. So himſelfe profeſſeth in his Booke <hi>de
Miſſa Priuata.</hi> That all men might takeheed of following him, who
profeſſeth himſelf to follow the diuell.</p>
               <p n="9">9. Becauſe the Proteſtant Cauſe is now, &amp; hath
been from the beginning, maintained with groſſe falfifications, and
Calumnies; whereof their prime Controuerſie writers, are notoriouſly, and
in high degree guiltie.</p>
               <p n="10">10. Becauſe by denying all humane authority, either of
Pope, or Councels, or Church, to determine Controuerſies of Faith, they haue
aboliſhed all poſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble meanes of ſuppreſsing Hereſie, or reſtoring
vnity to the Church.</p>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:1936:20"/>
               <p>Theſe were the <hi>Anſwerers Motiues;</hi> and they are good
ones indeed, and ſo ſtrong, that he could neuer ſince frame his minde to
<hi>Proteſtancie:</hi> And the Profeſsion of Catholicke Religion, not
ſuting with his deſires &amp; deſignes, as I ſaid before, he fell vpon
<hi>Socinia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſme,</hi> that is, a <hi>No Religion.</hi> I will not here
ponder the foreſaid <hi>Motiues:</hi> only I muſt ſay, as I noted in the
pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent Chapter, that ſince they all (except perchance the laſt) chiefly
concerne matter of <hi>Fact,</hi> rather then any ſubtile points of
<hi>Doctrine,</hi> he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not with any probable ſhew of reaſon, retract
them, and if he ſhould, yet who would not ſooner credit his ſinceritie,
whilſt he ſpeakes, againſt the current of the times, in this place, and
contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to worldlie hopes, then now, when all human reſpects concurre to
ſway his words, profeſsion, and carriage,
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>en contrary to his inward
thoughts! But in the meane time, it would be ſport, to behold <hi>Doctor
Potter</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futing theſe <hi>Motiues</hi> of the <hi>Anſwerer,</hi>
while he is pretending to defend <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor Potter.</hi> And it may well
ſeeme a <pb n="41" facs="tcp:1936:20"/>ſtrange and prepoſterous zeale in the
<hi>Anſwerer</hi> (if he haue any regard to the Church of <hi>England</hi>)
to haue been ſo long careleſſe in remouing this ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dall againſt
<hi>Proteſtants,</hi> and anſwering his owne <hi>Motiues;</hi> and yet now
to ſhew ſuch feruour in writing againſt others: which whether he doe of
his owne accord, or by entreatie of <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor Potter,</hi> or from ſome
<hi>Higher com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand,</hi> I am neither certaine, nor ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitous. My hartie
wiſhes are, that whoſoeuer ſhall reade theſe <hi>Motiues,</hi> may, for
the eternall good of his owne Soule, conſider them with indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rencie, and
at leaſure, and neuer reſt from ſolliciting the learnedſt
<hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants,</hi> either to giue him ſatisfaction (which is
impoſsible to be donne.) or els not take it ill, if he haſten to the One,
alwaies. Viſible, Catholicke, Apoſtolicke, Roman Church; out of which none
can, without preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, hope to be ſaned, and of which Bleſſed<note n="*" place="margin">Cont. part. Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nati Pſal.</note> 
                  <hi>Saint
Auſtin</hi> ſaith: <hi>Nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Sace: dotes vel ab ipſa Petri ſede;
&amp; in ordine illo Patrum, quis cui ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit, videte. Ipſa eſt
Petra, quam non <pb n="42" facs="tcp:1936:21"/>vincunt ſuperba inferorum portae;</hi>
Rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kon the Prieſts, euen from the very Sea of <hi>Peter;</hi> and ſee, who
ſucceeded one another in that ranke of Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. That is the Rocke, againſt
which the proud gates of Hell doe not preuaile. ⸫</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:1936:21"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
